I bow to all the seekers of truth.
At the very outset
we have to know
that truth is what it is.
We cannot organise it,
we cannot conceptualise it;
we also unfortunately
cannot know it
at this human awareness.
That’s why
in all scriptures it is said
that you are to be born again.
But it is not just a certificate one can take
that “I’m born again.”
It is something
that is a real state
within us,
that gives you the right
to say you are born again.
At the very outset again I would
like to say one more thing,
that whatever I’m telling you here
has to be
understood
as scientist. It’s a scientific outlook.
Don’t accept everything
that I am saying,
blindfolded.
But scientific attitude is such that
if I am putting before you a hypothesis
and if you find that
it is working out,
it is being proved, then
as honest people you must accept,
because it is for
your emancipation and for the
emancipation of the whole world.
We have to realise
that we are not at the point
where we know the absolute truth
and the absolute knowledge.
Absolute means, when
there is not the other.
If we had known the absolute
we would never have
had all these problems,
these fightings and wars,
different ideologies
propounded all over the world,
but we all would have
felt the same thing,
understood the same thing,
and we would have been all one
as far as our understanding
of the truth was concerned.
That’s what you find among saints.
They are all of the same style,
of the same type, talk
of the same thing,
in the same way.
But whatever they have
known in their lifetime
has not been yet delivered
to the common people,
and that’s why so many of
them misunderstood them
and they were crucified,
they were killed and tortured.
The time has come for us
now, a special time,
when the common person
has to know about it.
Formerly
in India we had three
type of institutions,
as far as the Divine was concerned.
One we call as the
right side of Vedas.
“Veda” itself comes
from the word “vidh”
means “to know on your
central nervous system.”
It’s not mental;
you have to know it on your
central nervous system.
And this
was also shown
in the early Christians,
when Thomas has written
a beautiful treatise
which were found about
fifty years back in Egypt,
that he called
Christians as “Gnostics.”
“Gn”, “gn” word comes from the word
“gn” or “dnya” in Sanskrit language,
meaning “the knowledge.”
Knowledge is not mental
land according to this book
which is now being rewritten,
knowledge is an experience on
our central nervous system.
So we have to understand
that in our evolutionary process
whatever we have achieved
is felt on your
central nervous system.
For example, a dog or
an animal, any animal
if you want, can pass through
any dirty, filthy place
without feeling anything about it.
But a human being cannot,
because in his evolutionary process
he has developed a new awareness
of cleanliness, of beauty,
of virtues, of sublimity.
In the same way now we have to
have the last breakthrough of
our evolutionary process,
where we have to become the spirit.
The spirit is
within our heart.
It’s the witness of what we are doing.
But it has not yet come
into our attention,
and so this is the
mechanism within us
which is built in during all our
evolutionary process one by one.
And now the time is for you
to get the last breakthrough through
that point, as you see clearly,
is the actualisation of the baptism,
where you do feel the cool
breeze of the Holy Ghost.
The Holy Ghost is reflected
in the triangular bone as kundalini.
These centres are on your
central nervous system.
We can say they are looked,
they are the sources of
parasympathetic nervous system,
and there’s left and right
sympathetic nervous systems
which are nourished by the left
and the right, two channels.
In one lecture, I am sorry,
I won’t be able to tell
you all about this thing.
But luckily they have
agreed to have a follow-on,
in which they will have people who
want to know more about it
enrolled, and they would like
to give you a course
of about seven weeks,
every night once a week. And if
that happens you can gain a lot.
And if that happens
you can gain a lot.
But one thing I must tell
you at the very outset:
you cannot pay for it,
you cannot, because
it’s a living process.
Try to understand, logically, when
it’s a living process we don’t pay.
For example, see these
beautiful flowers are here.
We take them for granted.
See the beautiful area
you have in Canberra,
now the autumn has come.
Autumn comes, the beautiful colours of
ochre, this, that, I’m just enjoying.
All that comes by itself,
the seasons come by itself.
You don’t pay anyone for that.
You don’t pay the Mother Earth
for giving you these flowers.
In the same way
when you have become
a human being,
you have not paid at
all for your evolution.
Then how can you pay
for a higher awareness?
Is a logical thing
you should understand.
You cannot pay for
this living process,
and nor for this knowledge. All right,
you can pay for this hall, is all right;
but you cannot pay
for this happening.
You cannot pay for
anything that is divine.
If you understand this point you’ll
have to understand also another point:
it has to be very effortless.
If it is so vital,
it is so important, it
has to be effortless.
With a very little effort you should
be able to achieve your evolution.
If that doesn’t happen,
that you should know that it is
something else, but not your evolution.
Now, you have to know
what you are seeking
is the truth.
And what is the truth is,
actually you are seeking your
higher evolutionary attainment.
That is, to be the spirit is the
first truth you are seeking.
And the second one is that
all this living work is done
by an all-pervading Power,
that’s the divine love.
They may call it by the
name “Paramachaitanya”,
they may call it as the
"Cool breeze of the Holy Ghost,"
they can call it as the
"All-pervading Power of God’s Love" or
they can call it as
the “Ruh” or anything.
But it is a fact
that all this living work is done
through this vital power
which combines all the
powers of the world.
This power has created us
and this power wants us to
feel that power,
to get connected with that power,
to be enriched by that power,
to enjoy that power,
and then ultimately to use it
to give it to others also.
We are human beings and
we get so frustrated with
ourselves sometimes,
people start asking, “Why am I here,
for what? What’s my purpose?
After all this useless thing I’m
going on with the insurance;
so much to be paid, the bills
to be paid, this to be paid!”
You are fed up.
Is a fact, no doubt, I agree.
But you have forgotten
your purpose, that’s why.
Actually within yourself you
are extremely beautiful.
Your divinity is waiting for you.
In your depth you have all that.
You have to reach that divinity.
Then you will know how
beautiful you are,
how dynamic you are,
how compassionate you are,
and that how universal you are.
All this has to come to
you through this connection.
I’ll tell a story about taking a,
say, a television set
to a very remote village in India
where they have never known
anything about television.
You show them the box and
they’ll say, “What, this box?”
If you tell them, “No, you can
see lots of pictures in this
from all over the world,”
they’ll say, “What, this box?”
That’s what we feel
about ourselves.
But once this box is put to the mains,
then you know how fantastic is it.
Then you realise how great you are.
And this knowledge
has to be our own.
It has only been made possible now.
Luckily, something has happened to
this all-pervading Power that
it has become so dynamic,
and it is helping us to get
you all as seekers.
I say you are a special
category of people
who are seeking truth.
This category has to be
faced by every country,
every nation, every government.
You cannot stop them from seeking.
But in that seeking they have gone to
drugs, they have gone to alcoholism,
they have gone to
all kinds of madness,
and also to false people.
They have suffered so much.
People come to Me and yesterday
there was three people;
and they told Me, “Mother,
they went to this guru here,
someone, and they are
so much suffering.”
I don’t mind, if they want
to make money, let them make,
because there are so many thieves in
this world, you know, can’t help it.
All right. But it’s not only
that: they spoil your kundalini,
they spoil your kundalini,
they spoil your
chances of realisation
and they give you diseases.
They give you serious diseases
of such a horrible nature that
sometimes I really give up. I say,
“Now how am I to help them?”
And we listen to them and
believe them, blindfolded.
So in this short time, what
I can warn you, this way:
that first of all
before going to anyone like that,
you must find out
what other disciples
who are there have got,
what powers have they got,
how they behave.
Are they beautiful people,
have they really become
religious or righteous,
have they really become? Because
you can follow any religion
Hindu, Muslim, Christian, any religion;
you can commit any sins.
How these people are,
how they are living among themselves,
what are their relations
with each other?
Once in a while we
might also get somebody
who is a money-maker or something,
but we throw them out.
We throw them out. Maybe
sometimes we might
get somebody, you see, just
like a outsider coming in,
but such people are then thrown out.
So you have to see the body
of such organisation,
how it works,
what is the way these people are,
what have they achieved?
What about their children,
what about their families?
Everything you can
find out first and
then you should go to
anyone who talks about God.
That’s first thing: have
they got godliness?
Because William Blake has said,
"There will be a special category of
people who will be born on this Earth."
He calls them, “Men of God.”
They will know God, and
they’ll make others godly.
Now with Sahaja Yoga
you get so many powers.
The first and foremost is that you
yourself get completely physically cured.
So many diseases are
cured by Sahaja Yoga.
But it’s not a guarantee.
If you get your realisation and if
you settle down in Sahaja Yoga,
you don’t have to get to any diseases.
It’s possible: we have worked it out,
it has worked even in Australia,
it has worked in India.
There are two doctors
who have got M.D. in Sahaja
Yoga in Delhi University.
There are seven doctors in England,
who are experimenting, means
they are documenting how many
people have been cured.
We have such a lot of documentation
that we don’t know how
to even transport it.
And there are forty doctors in Russia
who are following Sahaja Yoga.
I must say, unfortunately
Australia is one country
where they never understood us.
I’ve been coming here
from the year 1978.
Unfortunately at that time all
these gurus were here prevalent,
and nobody would accept us because
we are not charging any money.
And it was impossible
to tell them about it.
They would just walk out as soon as
I said we don’t take any money.
It was really very
difficult to communicate.
And as a result we have very few
Sahaja yogis, specially in Canberra,
and the report is that they come
but they just disappear.
But if they have commitment
of money then they stick on,
because you paid for it, you see.
Like you go to see some funny film
or some funny drama
and you don’t like it,
but still you stick on
because you paid for it.
Is a human psychology. But I say,
how much can you pay for it?
How much can you pay for
it? It’s so invaluable.
You see, you cannot
measure it in money.
God doesn’t understand money,
He doesn’t understand banks. This is
your headache, it’s not His headache.
So, once we understand one
thing: it’s a pure thing,
it’s so pure. Reality
cannot be purchased;
you have to know it.
So, now these centres are here,
as you see: he must have told
you about them one by one.
And when you come to this course they
will tell you all about it in details,
and within, I’m sure, seven weeks
you all will become great
masters of Sahaja Yoga.
And you can cure people,
you can raise their kundalini.
Not only raise their kundalini, but
you can
understand this subtle
knowledge in no time.
It really increases your capacity
of your intelligence
so much that we have
had children who came
to us as dullards
and now they are scoring so well,
they have records.
Not in India, even in Australia
they are doing so well.
Now in England which is, which
has got a disease of unemployment,
in Sahaja Yoga it’s hard to find
even one person who is unemployed;
because we don’t think that taking
dole is a very respectable thing.
So suddenly they get their
jobs and they work it out.
It’s something that happens: a person
becomes so dynamic, so relaxed.
Now these days there
are so many diseases
about which I need
not tell you;
but specially the
tension that you have,
because I was told most of
them are bureaucrats here.
My husband has been a
bureaucrat all his life,
so I know what it is.  I know
the bureaucrats very well.
This tension comes to us
because we work too much on the
right side, as you see there,
this yellow line.
And that develops onto another
horrible thing called as ego:
that we feel we are doing
it. There’s nothing wrong,
it’s nothing wrong, because
ignorance gives you
that idea that “I am doing this work.”
There’s nothing wrong in feeling that way.
But what happens that
when kundalini rises,
she pushes that down
and makes, I call it as a 'chimney,'
because that’s what they
understand in English language,
that it makes like an opening here.
And this opening takes away
all the heat of the work
and the idea that “I
am doing this work.”
You just don’t feel you are doing it;
it’s so relaxed.
All these problems that you have,
as the bureaucrats specially,
I will explain to you
what problems they have.
In this short time whatever is
possible I’ll try to give you.
Now, we work on the right
side: they’re bureaucrats
it's because they’re planning,
because they’re thinking too much.
They are futuristic people, planning,
planning, planning like mad.
Not only, but their nature
becomes such a planning,
that if they are going on the road,
immediately they’ll say, “Oh, they
should have put this signboard here.
They should have done that there. They
should have put this tree there.”
I mean, you are not doing that job at all,
you see, you are nothing to do with it.
But they’ll go on thinking for others
also what they should have done,
what it is should be
done, that should be done.
So all the time thinking, thinking
makes them mad, with this...
with this right side
developing too much,
they become work alcoholics,
and they are very unkind in
the family also because,
you see, they are so
irritable sometimes.
And sometimes they try to
push back the temper,
and that’s how they
become even worse.
Because this, this centre, this is
a very special centre within us:
we call it as Swadishthan.
This centre outside, in the...
we can say in the physical way
or in the medical terminology,
acts through our aortic plexus.
I studied medicine forty years back
so but now, they might
have changed the name,
but we used to know as aortic plexus.
This aortic plexus looks after this...
viscera as you see there, whole
thing, all that, all the viscera.
And here is one, first one, is the liver.
Now liver is the one that’s
very important in our body,
which is responsible for taking out
all the poison of the body as heat,
and deliver it into the bloodstream.
But when this centre is doing
something else much more important,
then it is neglected
Now, what is this
important thing we do,
that this centre also has a responsibility
to supply energy to the brain
or supply even some cells,
fat cells, for the displacement
of the used-out cells
and nourishing them with new cells.
So when we think too
much all the time,
this poor centre gets very busy,
and it has no time for your liver.
So the liver gets into trouble.
Now when the liver gets heated
up, the heat passes upward.
When it passes upward, it touches the
centre that we call it as the right heart.
This centre when is heated up,
then the lungs start getting
coagulated and you develop asthma.
Of course, it has also due to
the effect of the left side which
I’ll tell you later on which,
which triggers it, which
triggers this asthma.
Now this asthma
once settled in cannot be cured
by any means but by Sahaja Yoga.
We have cured, I mean, not I
would say I have cured, but
Sahaja Yoga has cured
through kundalini awakening,
asthma of a gentleman
who was an architect.
Mostly architects also
are of the same style:
they get asthma, very common,
and there’s another disease they
get which I’ll tell you later on,
and that is also a result of
this kind of over-thinking.
Now when you neglect
your liver, also the
heat passes downward.
When it passes downward
it catches your kidneys.
And the kidneys get coagulated
and they cannot function,
so you get kidney trouble. And the
doctors don’t want to tell you the truth
but I would like to tell you,
that dialysis can never cure you.
And it’s such an expensive thing, you
become bankrupt and die, that’s all.
So for that, what is the
treatment?  Is in Sahaja Yoga.
We have been able to see that people
get cured of their kidney trouble
with a very simple
method of Sahaja Yoga.
Because we are dealing with
the fundamental thing:
like if there’s a tree which is sick
if you want to apply some
medicine on the leaves
it doesn’t work out; you
have to go to the roots
So we go to the roots very
easily through your kundalini,
and it works out.
Now there’s another
disease they develop,
because the heat can
pass to the left side.
Now supposing
somebody who is young
and he’s very ambitious and is sort
of a sportsman, we can call him,
playing tennis or
football or such a game,
and drinking too much.
All this creates heat very much,
and may get a massive heart
attack at a very young age,
and it’s absolutely vital.
Also such people get heart attacks
of the massive type later on, who have
got this problem of too much working.
There’s another kind of a
heart attack we call angina,
due to lethargic heart which is,
which comes from the left side.
They are two things, one is
the left and another is right
and when we confuse them we do not
know what to treat what person.
But in Sahaja Yoga you can easily find
out a person is right-sided or left-sided,
or is it psychosomatic:
means combination of both.
It’s very simple to find out.
Now then the another horrible disease
that comes to a person who is
sitting on the table and
planning, is diabetes.
It’s very common.
If a woman also is diabetic, her
child can get it as an inheritance.
Now this diabetes comes to you as a result
because you think too much and you
neglect, the pancreas is neglected.
This pancreas is responsible for looking
after your problems of diabetes.
And when it is done then what you get is
a collapse of this pancreas in a way,
and you start getting
this diabetes in you.
Here also the left-side
triggering is done
when you get diabetes. But diabetes
also is quite curable in Sahaja Yoga.
If you practice it properly every day,
morning, evening, five
minutes in the morning
and ten minutes in the
evening, it works out.
Now the other disease that you
get is much more dangerous is,
is the blood cancer.
It comes from the spleen which
is again neglected by this centre
and you lead a very, very hectic life.
Actually all the bureaucrats are on,
on very highly strung notes
and they are very hectic also.
Early in the morning they will, they
cannot get up, they are so tired.
So they get up just about
ten minutes before the work,
somehow or other
push their clothes in
and just rush out; the wife
runs with the breakfast too!
And they get into the car
and then they see a jam,
and they get so upset.
Now they are so time-bound
that’s again problem.
They are so time-bound.
And in these days when
there is so much of
jam and all that on the street and they
get so frustrated, they are so hectic.
All this hectic-ness leads us
into a very funny situation,
because this spleen
is responsible for creating RBCs,
that is red blood corpuscles,
whenever you are in emergency.
When you are in emergency,
then this starts working more.
For example, if you have taken your food
and if you start running, you’ll get a pain,
terrible pain on this side.
That’s because your spleen
has gone into action,
it's producing more
red blood corpuscles.
So this hectic life
that you have today,
you make this poor spleen a
crazy one because she doesn’t
know what this man is up to.
Suddenly he becomes so
much excited and he
gets into emergency, then
again he gets into emergency,
so this spleen gets
absolutely into problem.
And when again some
triggering takes place,
then you develop this blood cancer.
But the another, as I told you,
the kidney, and a person who is like this
is suffering always from constipation.
Because it also, heat goes down and it
makes this lower end into a kind of a
very dry, dry thing
and that’s how people suffer from
terrible constipation sometime.
This is a little bit that I’ve told, that
a bureaucrat is capable of suffering.
Also is possible, paralysis;
paralysis he gets on the right side.
Also he might get a
frozen arm, right arm
frozen, all sorts of things:
migraines because of bad liver,
and cirrhosis of the liver,
cancer of... the other day we met one
fellow who had cancer of the liver.
And the doctor said, “You are a gone case.”
I found out he’s a very
big boss somewhere.
I said, “Now you’d better resign for
a while, and then I’ll work it out.”
So all these things
are to be understood
in a proper way
and we have to treat
ourselves with respect.
We have to govern our body properly.
In Sahaja Yoga you’ll
get all the knowledge
that is necessary for you to
know about your wellbeing,
first of all.
And then you will also know
how to keep yourself all right.
Now this is something that
I have told you already,
but the left-side triggering takes
place when you go to wrong places
like this and to wrong gurus:
they, I think, mesmerise you
or I don’t know what they do.
Their styles I don’t understand,
because they do not tell you the
modus operandi as to what they do,
while you’ll know the complete
modus operandi of Sahaja Yoga.
You yourself become masters of this.
If you use a little
assiduity, if you little bit work it out,
I’m sure you yourself will be surprised
how you have become your masters.
But this is only the
physical side of it.
Even emotionally those
people who have suffered,
like epilepsy and also you
can say mental disorders
and all that, have
been very much helped,
because that’s the left
side will work out.
Now the psychosomatic
diseases are like...
We call them, even
diabetes, as psychosomatic
because there’s a effect of the left
on them; or myelitis and all this,
what you call it, the disability of the
muscles to work out, all these things,
and recently another disease
called as the yuppies’ disease.
I had, I had
told them beforehand, five years
before this disease came in.
I had also told them about the AIDS.
But as I was not taking any money,
Americans were not interested.
Because Americans are so
proud of their money;
they think, “How can we
not purchase this woman?”
Moreover when I went to America, you’ll
be surprised, they asked Me a question,
“How many Rolls-Royces You have?”
I said, “I have none.”
They said, “We are not interested
in You. You have no business.”
I said, “I have no business.
There’s no business about it.”
But this is difficult to make
them understand, Americans,
that God is not a business.
They want to make business
out of everything,
and now see the situation there
of the business that they did:
what is their situation is not very good.
So whatever, even the
business you are doing,
even the economic side of it, has to be understood
that we have to have a balance.
If we don't have a balance, we
cannot achieve anything in life.
And this imbalancing has taken us to
this ecological problem, this problem.
Actually most of this problem,
all these universal problems,
if you see, all these global
problems, come from human beings.
You know My husband has been
working with this U.N.
and he agrees with Me entirely:
it all comes from human beings.
And if this transformation
can take place,
we don’t even have to have
U.N., you just become united
within, not outside, but
you just become united.
And this is what you achieve
is a collective consciousness,
a new awareness within you.
You start feeling the cool breeze
in your hands, the vibrations,
very soothing,
and you can feel the
centres of all the persons.
And you can also feel your centres
and you know how to correct
them, yours and others.
This is a new awareness that comes
to you as collective consciousness.
Thank God, Jung has already talked
about it, that if you have to evolve,
you will evolve into a new awareness
as collective consciousness, and
in Sanskrit language it is
called as “samuhik chetana.”
The first state where you reach
is out of this Agnya Chakra:
when you cross over
to the limbic area,
you become thoughtlessly aware.
You are aware, but thoughtless. So
you become a very peaceful person.
People who have got peace awards,
I haven’t seen them, seen
such hot-tempered people.
I don’t know, from where did
they get this peace award?
Extremely hot-tempered: you can’t
go near them without a
barge-pole, you know!
Any time they are willing
to have a hit at you.
And they have got peace awards,
Nobel awards, this,
that. I mean, I
don’t know from what angle they
got, get all these things,
what is the judgment point is.
So one has to know that
the peace has to be within,
and this peace is established. You
become a witness of the whole drama.
You start seeing the
whole thing as a drama.
You are away from the problems and
that’s how you can solve the problems,
and once you become an expert you can
help others to solve the problems.
It’s something awaiting us.
We all have to rise to that level, and
to get to that state where
we can really have that
special status which is meant for us.
Is your right to have it.
As a result, you’ll be
surprised, you’ll be so free
and so capable to enjoy the freedom.
People don’t even enjoy their freedom
because they are not capable.
Like, you see, our democracy
has become demonocracy,
because we don’t know
how to enjoy our freedom,
we don’t know how to
balance our freedom.
But after that, what happens,
automatically you become so free
I mean, you get rid of all your habits.
In England I, first time
when I started My work,
I got seven hippies,
all drenched in drugs.
But they were brought like
dead pieces before Me.
And overnight they
gave up their drugs.
I said, “Look at that!
How is it possible?”
They had not established
their Sahaja Yoga so far,
but they gave up their drugs, all
right. An example is like this,
that supposing you are
holding onto a snake
and you have no capacity to give it up,
and moreover you are obstinate.
There’s all darkness, you can’t see;
somebody tells you it’s a snake.
You won’t give it up till it bites you,
till you are dead. So
if there’s a little light in you,
immediately you, yourself throw it away.
I don’t have to tell you anything;
you do it yourself everything.
You become your own
masters. You guide yourself
because you are great, as I’ve told you,
but you have to touch your divinity.
And it should not be, like
as we have in the schools,
a mathematical proposition
in smaller classes they used to
say, a house was to be built,
'A’ came for one day, ran away,
'B’ came for two days, ran away, and
third came for half a day and ran away.
When will the work be over? Never,
is the answer! Because if you
have such run-away people,
how can you have the house being built?
I mean, it’s not possible, mathematically
it is not possible, but it might be
imaginary, you might think like that.
So you have to pay some
attention to your realisation,
you have to pay to yourself,
and to your ascending.
I don’t know how many
you are here today,
and I feel sorry that
we didn’t have a hall;
because last time we had a big hall
and it was practically empty,
so we thought this time we
should have a smaller hall.
It was a miscalculation
completely on our behalf,
I must say, and I am sorry for this,
that you all have to stand like this.
But I’m sure whatever
may be the situation
we all will get realisation today.
You should have full
confidence in yourself
that we are all going to
get our Self-realisation.
Of course, I would like you
to ask Me some questions
for a very...   because we started little late
because of this music and all that,
but I would like you to ask Me
some questions for a while,
and then we’ll have this
process of Self-realisation
As far as the questions are
concerned I would say that,
that I am not here to take
anything away from you,
but I’m here just to give
you the key of your own being,
to know yourself. So
ask relative questions,
not aggressive ones,
because I’m very good at
answering, I must tell you,
because I’ve been now
answering questions
for the last twenty
years all over the world.
So I’m quite clever and I’ll
answer all your questions.
But it’s a mental feat, again I’ll say it:
that is no guarantee that
you’ll get your realisation,
that is no guarantee. So
it’s just a mental feat.
If you have any sensible question
please ask Me, because I don’t want
at the time of realisation suddenly
your mind comes up and says,
“Now, hey, you didn’t ask
this question to Mataji.”
So please, whatever is possible, we’ll
take about fifteen minutes for that,
and after that we’ll have a realisation
which will take hardly ten to
fifteen minutes, that’s all.
I hope you have all that patience. After
that I would like to meet all of you today.
Those who get realisation
I would like to meet you,
because I may not be back
here for one year at least.
May God bless you.
Questions?
There’s one thing I would like to suggest,
that those who are Sahaja
yogis can go and stand,
and those who are not
can come and sit down.
It’s better that the Sahaja
yogis can go and stand there.
Those who are not Sahaja yogis
yet should come here, this side,
and please be seated.
Sahaja yogis can stand now.
If the kundalini is awakened are you
then more sensitive to other people
and their ailments and
the ailments of yourself
Yes, of course, that’s what I said.
Not only aware, but you know
each and everything about them:
not outward things but their centres, you
know what’s wrong with their centres.
So when you say that the
Pentecost got their realisation,
when the Holy Ghost blessed them, they
started talking in some other language
it’s not Latin or Hebrew,
but they started talking in the
language of chakras or centres,
as we also talk the same way.
Traditionally in the literature of India
when we look at the
information about kundalini,
it appears to be a very
difficult and arduous process.
It’s true.
So what has occurred in
1970 or since then,
that now makes it accessible to everybody?
Yah!  You see, it’s true, it’s very difficult.
If something very difficult
is done by someone,
then there must be something
about it, isn’t it?
It is very difficult.
And once, a guru of
Shivaji was asked
how much time does it take
for kundalini to rise.
He used the word, Sanskrit word,
“tat kshan” ” means “that moment.”
But there should be a
person who is able to give
and the one who is able to receive it;
and that’s all ready now, I
think, so it’s working out.
You are capable of receiving, and I
think I am quite capable of giving!
Inaudible question
I didn't hear.
She said she has experienced
She’s just standing.
No, no, yes in front.
This way?
No, no, no.
The light you can bring it down
a little bit at least, you see.
I never used to use spectacles,
but because of these lights
all the time on My eyes.
Ha, now, better.
She says she has experienced kundalini
and she’s experienced
an increase in energy,
but she doesn’t know
what to do with it.
She was in Sahaja Yoga?
You got it in Sahaja Yoga?
Where?
Anand Marg in [unclear]
Ah, impossible! They can’t give
you. Anand Marg, of all the things?
Ah!
less said the better
about them, Madam.
It’s a very dangerous
cult you have joined,
the most dangerous. Yah,
you see...  [unclear]
No, no, not at all. He’s incapable.
They are incapable of doing.
They are very violent people,
extremely violent. They were
banned in India for years together
and the gentleman was put in jail,
and not only that but now his own wife
and his own son has joined Sahaja Yoga.
It’s so terrible as that.
You see, it’s a very violent
organisation. But it’s surprising...
And is that why You say
why I can’t do anything?
Yah, no, not at all. How
can you? No, not all.
You see, because the
energy you must be feeling
is not that energy, but of
the sympathetic nervous system
I will see about you now.
Do you feel the cool
breeze in your hands?
Do you feel the cool breeze
on top of your head?
Yes, I feel like some
string is holding me, like
No!
Not that way. It’s very simple, yah.
So those who have followed Anand
Marg, it’s very dangerous, I must say.
I don’t want to discuss all these things
but it’s absolutely illegal stuff, horrible.
When...  Once I was with My husband
in one of the hotels, and two people
came with policemen to see Me.
I was quite shocked,
and C. P. being a
bureaucrat he didn’t
understand the police
coming to see us, you see.
The police people told us that
these two people, husband
and wife, want to see You.
And they wanted police
protections so we've come.
I asked them, “Why?
What’s wrong with you?
So what's...
They were very active.
His name was...
What was his name, Dr... ?
Dr. Prasad!
He was a very active man.
He even came to Australia
for this work, and he went also
to America and all those places.
And he discovered that there
were twenty-eight deaths
which he could not explain.
And he got such a shock,
and he said that he went to a temple
where he suddenly felt that
he was doing all wrong.
So he talked to people
about it, whatever he knew.
And he ran away with
his wife in a jeep
and came to Lucknow, and
from there he came to Delhi.
There somebody told him, “You’d
better see Mother about it.”
So he came to see Me, but he
had this police protection.
So he came, and he told Me
how these murders took place
and what all happened.
Then the mother, the wife of this
gentleman, Mr. Sarkar, and his son,
both of them came to Sahaja Yoga, and
they are very active Sahaja yogis today.
And the lady tells Me how
terrible things he has done.
And he has amassed money, amassed.
And this lady told Me, “I don’t want
to take a single pai out of that.”
He made a will, he, I think at
the end of life he must have felt
that “I should give something
to my wife and child.”
They refused to have anything
to do with that money.
They said, “We know from
where this money has come.”
It’s the most violent organisation.
another question [unclear]
He said, “You say that You
are born again. Is that true?"
I... I didn’t say that, did I?
[unclear]
You cannot certify. I said it
is a state you have to reach.
When you are born again
you have all these
powers which I described
to you, minimum.
You cannot just say “I’m
born again.” All right?
This is the point is.
[unclear]
What's this?
He’s saying, the
second question is,
Are You saying that You
do not know the truth,
or we do not know the truth?
I know the truth, I
should say very humbly,
and you will also know
the truth.  All right?
There was one man who actually said He
was the truth, and that was Jesus Christ.
And we know Jesus
Christ also very well,
much better than any one of
you, which you will also know.
But He’s my saviour.
Yes, He is, He is there, and whatever
He has said is to be proved.
Otherwise what is
Christianity doing today?
I was Myself born in
a Christian religion
and I know all about it. Do you know the...
There is one thing Jesus
said, He said He is the way
He might have said anything, but
Christians are not doing that.
Please!  [unclear]
Yes, but you are not. You see, you
but first of all understand that
are we practicing what Christ has said?
First question!
We are not.
Christ has said, “Thou shall
not have adulterous eyes.”
Let Me see who is that Christian?
But I can say all My Sahaja
yogis are like that.
They have innocent eyes.
We are not following what Christ
has said that’s the mistake.
You are just organising Christ.
You cannot organise a
personality like Christ.
You don’t know
anything about Christ.
Christ is a very great personality.
Only for four years He lived
actually in the public,
and they crucified Him; and
they are again crucifying Him
in the name of Christianity
and Christians, take it from Me.
I can’t understand that Vatican itself
printed
securities worth two billion dollars.
What is they call, securities of what?
What these are? Securities of what these were?
To do with the Vatican bank
Yes in the...  Yes "Mafia" with the Mafia
with the help of Mafia.
They sold it! False, absolutely false!
Do you mean they are following Christ,
the one who took a hunter in His
hand and whipped all the people
who are selling things?
Are they following Christ?
He was a carpenter; did He
take any money from anyone?
We take Christ into our pockets,
think that He is our own.
It’s like all these great incarnations
who were born on this Earth
to prepare you for your last resurrection.
He has said, “I will send you
the Holy Ghost.” What about that?
The question is, what
about the Holy Ghost?
They don’t know anything
about the Holy Ghost.
You will, you will know. See, as Christians...
Excuse Me, sir, as Christians
what have you achieved?
Nothing. What have you achieved?
What is the question?
Ah?
going around in circles.
You are going round in circles.
Now you better sit. Be seated.
You must understand humbly one thing:
as Christian you have
not achieved anything,
but as Sahaja yogi you
will achieve Christ.
If I promise you that, I will
show you that, all right?
Jesus said that He is the only way.
Yes, it’s true. He is the only way and
that’s what we are going to prove,
that He is the only way.
But we are going to prove
that. You cannot prove it.
You say Jesus is the only way,
Muslims will say that
Mohammed is the only way,
Hindus will say Krishna is the only way;
everybody saying they are the only way.
This is all fundamentalism, nothing else.
This is absolute fundamentalism
and not understanding Christ.
Christ has said, “Those who are not
against Me are with Me.” Who are those?
He has also said for these Christians,
“You’ll be calling Me “Christ,
Christ and I won’t recognise you.”
Clearly, in the second chapter
and second verse of Matthews.
It was Paul who ruined
Christianity, and then Augustine.
And you know in England what
they are talking about Him?
That He was a homosexual. Oh, how
dare they say such things about Him?
Horrible things they are saying
about a divine personality
which they do not understand a word.
It’s all minting money,
and paying people some
money to preach about God.
How can you pay money
to preach about God?
Try to understand.
In India they came with a gun in one hand
and a Bible in another hand. Imagine!
And even one gentleman
in a Calvinistic church
came with a pistol towards Me
and a Bible in the another hand.
I said, “Now put the Bible on one
side at least.” Raised the pistol!
Is this the way Christ, the
one who said that “forgive.”
He asked His Father to forgive
those who crucified Him?
You have not understood Christ at all.
You have made a
mess of His life,
and you have really brought
such bad name to Him.
Please understand.
By calling yourself Christians you
do not become. By following Him,
by practicing Him and that’s
what these people are doing.
They are doing all over the world.
You’ll be surprised, we have
so many people who are Jews
and they respect Christ,
they worship Christ.
Can you do that?
Because they know who He was.
These were all incarnations of the Divine,
and they were born as flowers.
Please keep down your hand till I tell
you because it may, you may get tired.
So, these all flowers
came on the Tree of Life,
Tree of spirituality.
They were all nourished by the same.
But we plucked them,
and now these are dead
flowers we are fighting.
We should get rid of this
fundamentalism and this idea
that He was the only one, and He was
the only one, and He was the only one.
While Krishna has also said,
“Sarva dharmam parityajaya
mam ekam sharanam vraja.”
“Give up all religions and follow Me.”
So all the Hindus can say, “All right,
we are the ones who are chosen ones.”
All these chosen ones,
how they are behaving?
He didn’t say about truth [unclear]
If you think you are convinced, sir,
that you can do well with Christianity
you can leave the hall.
But I do not think that way.
Yes?
It’s there, there's a gentleman
there. Please get up.
All right? Thank you.
[Inaudible question]
Did you hear that?
He is saying that You say that the
kundalini is coming out all the time,
out into the all-pervading Power.
Some people say that
you should keep it in.
No, no, no, no. It’s a connection.
See now, as we have a connection for
this instrument, it’s a connection.
A connection has to be made.
If we, if this connection is kept
inside, how can we use this instrument?
Yes, please?
[Inaudible question]
You came to Sahaja Yoga, madam?
She came to Sahaja Yoga?
Unclear
We can’t be, we can’t
guarantee about others.
Yes, I must say I have experienced
the kundalini awakening,
but I can’t hold the state.
You see, the trouble is I don’t know
what sort of a kundalini
awakening you have got,
because whatever we know
is through Sahaja method.
We don’t know any other
method, all right?
So to keep up the state or go back
to whether you are realised or not,
we’ll have to check you. All right?
[Inaudible question]
We are all here to achieve
something for ourselves
but the world is
full of unhappiness,
and You talked about compassion.
How can an individual affect all
these terrible things in the world?
You are not an individual
any more, I must tell you.
Do you know, in Russia we have
thousands of people who
have got realisation.
That’s what I am saying,
here you do feel, because
Australia was not so kind to Me,
I should say, or kind to themselves.
But not otherwise.
We, this awakening is taking place very
fast and it’s spreading very fast,
and every candle that is enlightened
can enlighten another thousand candles.
So it’s not so. We have to change
the world only in this way;
there’s no other way out.
Through this transformation.
Shri Mataji asks Vinay to ask a Sahaja
Yogi to request their realisation.
Any other question, please?
[Inaudible question]
Could You tell us a little about the
traditions that this system is based on?
All right.
Now, the tradition is that we
had a group, we should say,
we called them as Nath Panthis  in India
who were working on the central path,
which is called as Sushumna.
But the tradition was that only one
guru could have only one disciple.
That was the tradition
for ages together.
And we had this Gorakhnath, and you
must have heard about the Machhindranath, Gorakhnath, Adinath,
all these people.
But only in the twelfth century
there was a great saint called Gyaneshwara,
and he begged of his
brother who was his guru,
that “please allow me at least to talk
about this in the local languages.”
Now in all the great books
in Sanskrit language,
like Yog Vasistha
and all these books
even in the sixth century
Adi Shankaracharya has
described about kundalini.
Everywhere it is described,
but in Sanskrit language.
Sanskrit language was only
read by very few people.
At the time of Rama, His
father-in-law was Janaka:
he was a great master of Sahaja Yoga,
and he gave realisation to only
one person called Nachiketa.
He’s mentioned there.
Then it was all limited.
But in the twelfth century Gyaneshwara
described it
in a treatise which he wrote about Gita,
Gyaneshwari, in the sixth chapter.
But the people whom we
call as dharma-markandas,
is the people who are in charge of
religion, couldn’t do anything about it.
So they said this is nishida,
means is not to be accepted,
it’s not to be read. So that
chapter were closed down.
In that he has written very clearly
that, “I have now said
as a great homage
to the spirit of the universe,
that now please give us the
blessings for the masses.”
And he’s described Sahaja Yoga very well:
what will happen when you get your blessings,
how the collective consciousness will
come and how people will evolve,
what will happen.
He did this on the twelfth century.
After that we had Kabira, we had Nanaka,
we had Ramadasa, we had Tukarama;
we had so many of saints
who have talked about it.
But still it could not go very further. Far!
Only two, three people used to get realisation.
Even “Buddha” itself means
“the realised soul.” Buddha,
Buddha, Buddha means from
bodha. “Bodha” means
“to know on your
central nervous system.”
So all of them said the same.
Even Christ has said it.
“You are to be born again.”
Clearly He has said it.
So we’ll have the certificate on
top: “We are born again.” Finished!
We don't go further with it.
We have to make enquiry:
what does this mean?
Because all these religions
were organised, you see.
You could not go out of this thing.
And those who tried to go were
thrown out of the religion.
Only in India the philosophy is
there, it’s not a religion as such.
I mean, you can say that the Sikhs,
the Jainies
and all of them are all in philosophy level;
it’s not organised at all. Nothing is organised.
The saints then came out of it
and they lashed all the society,
and they talked about the reality.
They have all talked about it in
their own vernacular languages.
Now, some of the songs they are singing was
written in the sixteenth century by Namadeva
I’ll ask them to sing this song.
It’s sung in every village,
where they are singing, “Oh Mother,
give us our realisation." Jogwa.
So we had this tradition in us.
But then these gurus
started coming up, because
they said we now have to have a guru.
Now, guru and a real guru, there
are descriptions already
given in vernacular languages.
Despite that, you see,
human beings are so great
that they can mess, make a
mess of everything, I tell you.
You give them anything beautiful,
they know how to make a mess.
And this is what they have done it.
Now let them get their realisation,
let them get perfected.
Let them get that subtle knowledge,
and then they can judge.
You become like a divine computer.
You can feel it on your
fingertips, the absolute truth.
You ask a question, “Was Christ
the son of God or not?”
Immediately you’ll start
feeling tremendous vibrations.
Even to take Christ’s name you will see.
The time has come for you
to prove all these things.
Otherwise everybody thinks they
are correct, like Saddam Hussein.
What’s wrong with him? He
thinks he was the chosen one,
by Mohammed Himself.
Then what can you do to such a person?
If you have such make-believes,
you cannot help it.
Hitler thought the same way.
But what is the criteria?
We live in a relative world.
We have to go to absolute.
If we accept this humbly,
then only we can have it. But if
you are satisfied with something
or your brain is washed
by some ideologies,
then I can’t help it.
But what good it has done to us?
Think it over.
While Hinduism, same thing,
where it is said that in
everybody it resides the spirit.
How can we have caste system?
This all came later on.
There’s a brahmin saint, a
great saint in India, Dasganu,
He says, “We have not known the Brahma.
We have not known this all-pervading
Power. How are we brahmins?”
There are so many instances to prove
that caste system is something
that is put on our head.
But it’s there,
and we have to fight it.
It’s the aptitude of a person.
It’s not inherent or it is not
prenatal;
it is just what type of thing you do.
I would say all Sahaja
yogis are the real brahmins,
because they know the Brahma.
You recommend meditation and chanting every day.
How long should one
maintain the chanting?
We have no chanting, madam, at all, no.
It spoils your throat.
Five minutes in the morning,
ten minutes in the evening:
is it too much of a time?
And chanting is another nonsense.
When you are not connected with
God, what are you chanting?
If your telephone is not working...
now see, we must be logical about it
what’s the use of telephoning?
Your telephone gets spoilt.
It’s so logical, I tell you.
Supposing now you have
the prime minister here
and you just go into his area
and start taking there his name,
they’ll all arrest you there.
You have to have connection.
But once you are in His Kingdom,
just remembering once is sufficient.
Even mantras:
they will just give you some
sort of a nonsensical mantra
like these T.M. people have
given you horrible mantras,
I must tell you this, horrible.
They are the worst, I think, as
far as money-making is concerned.
We had three people, four people.
One of them was the head
of their Flying Academy,
from Scotland.
His name is Peter Pierce, another his wife,
another his child, and fourth
one was the, his director.
They all came to Me with epilepsy.
Of course, now they are cured.
But poor things, they have all become
bankrupt and have gone to South Africa.
They are writing a book about it.
And they told Me about it,
and then many of them came.
Even we have some now in
Sydney and everywhere,
poor things suffering so much.
And they told Me that
three mantras were given.
One was “inga, pinga, tinga.”
Now any Indian here will know that
these are not Sanskrit words.
They’ll just start laughing at these things.
And they paid for each mantra three
hundred pounds, in those days.
Now “inga” means....
it’s a very colloquial village thing
because the guru who is there, he
doesn’t know any Sanskrit, nothing.
He was just a clerk;
I think he was a ticket collector.
Yah, he was a ticket collector in India.
But all the bureaucrats fell at his feet.
Do you know that? That’s the best part of it!
What is the bona fide of this man?
Now this fellow...   is the “inga” means
“scorpion bite”, is “inga”;
and “pinga” means when you
get possessed you go round
and round, it's “pinga”;
and “tinga” means this,
For that you pay three hundred pounds!
Then six thousand pounds were paid.
A barrister who had become mad,
her sister had become mad.
She was in lunatic asylum;
she was brought out, then now she is
cured. Both of them are all right.
Her name is Hester.
She told Me, “Six thousand pounds
they took from all of us.
We had to go to Switzerland in
very far-fetched horrible hotel,
and they put us there for this flying course.”
And they had to jump on some forms
and they all broke their bottoms,
to begin with.
But the food that was given to them,
for six days they had to drink water
which boiled the potatoes.
Then the seventh day they had to
take the rind of the potatoes.
And the eighth day the potatoes.
For six thousand pounds!
And this, I’m sure this guru must be
thinking how stupid these people are.
So he used to, he used to giggle all
the time. He could not help giggling.
And they are every time
marketing something new.
Now they are marketing here, what you
call, ayurveda. What is there to market?
Why do you need a guru for that?
And ayurveda cannot be
marketed in the West
in the real sense, because
you have to use fresh leaves.
You cannot.
One gentleman had a very bad
eczema. He was from Australia,
but then he came to England
and then he came to Russia.
I told him, “You have to come to India,
because I know one thing by
which it can be easily cured.
It’s a very simple leaf you have to use.”
And in three days he was all right.
So even if you have to practice
that, you don’t have to
have a guru for that.
Why do you? This is just
a marketing thing.
They’ll sell anything.
How can you sell anything?
Use your brains!
By God’s grace, you all have much
more brains than Indians have.
But we have much more
wisdom, I think,
because we have known
all this kind of thing.
And thank God, we don’t have
so much money to waste.
Our poverty is a blessing
to us, I think, in a way.
That’s why they have gone abroad.
They have formed groups,
they have formed this, that,
everywhere, and nobody would listen to Me.
In America they told Me, “You’d better go
back. Nobody is going to listen to You.”
Now let’s see how the
Australians are going to take it.
Thank God, I was born in a Christian religion,
because I can talk to
you about it very clearly.
My father joined Gandhiji. Immediately
he was thrown out of the church.
Because in India people, Christians,
mostly they are converted
from poor classes, you see.
So they think, they believe even now
that Christ was born in
England.
Can you beat that?
[Inaudible question]
No, you see, the meditation as I told
you is a little attention to yourself.
You are not to “do” meditation, but
you have to get into meditative mood.
As I told you, first you get into
the state of thoughtless awareness,
where you know everything
but there’s no thought. That
is, you are in the present.
You are neither in the
future nor in the past,
but you are the present
where there is no thought.
You watch everything,
you see everything;
but nothing you react. Just
there, you are seeing.
That’s a very great state,
because when you just see something...
now see, I look at these flowers.
Now if you are not a realised soul and
you look at these flowers, you think
from where they must
have got it now and
how much they must have paid,
all those things, what colours.
I don’t think like that; I just look at it.
And all the joy
that is put into it by the Creator
just starts flowing down
in the abstract way.
So that first state when you achieve,
in that state you start growing spiritually.
So achieve that state, you have
to pay attention to yourself.
Now if I say “Now you pay
attention to yourself,” you cannot.
All right. Now if I say the attention
is spread like then like this shawl,
and the kundalini is here: she
starts coming up like that.
So she puts your attention inside.
When she puts your attention inside
and she breaks this through,
then all this attention gets
enlightened and nourished by her.
This is to be seen within your life.
You see, if I tell somebody about
the beautiful place Canberra is,
nobody’s going to believe it
till they come and see it.
So better see it!
It’s very simple.
And moreover, see now in this place
there are so many lights, you see
and to just to switch them on
there must be one switch: just
switch on, all of them are there,
all right? But supposing I have to
tell you how all this was built
and how all this came here, and
how this electricity was invented
and how the source has been
built, you’ll get a headache.
So first thing you get your realisation,
get your light, then in that
light you see for yourself
and you, you are not a loser,
you don’t get into trouble,
nothing at all. So first
have it and then know.
All right?
You have not to be very
futuristic about it.
All right?
So I am happy that your
intellect is now satisfied.
You have to now help Me by
taking out your shoes,
because we have to take
help from the Mother Earth.
She is such an energy-giving thing.
So we can... No, it’s all right,
if you are sitting on the ground
you take out your shoes, that’s all.
If you are sitting on the ground you
are all right, take out just your shoes.
And also you'll feel comfortable.
Now Sahaja yogis, as I requested you,
can you go on the back side
and ask the people to come here?
[Marathi]
You can come this side.
Please, come this side.
There is room. Please come.
Move forward a little bit,
just a bit move forward. Yes
you can all move forward a little bit.
You have to a little bit adjust.
Sorry for this miscalculation.
Sahaja yogis can go out for the time being.
I want you all to sit down,
and sit down here closer to Me,
would be better.
If you sit there
it won’t help so much as
if you can come this side.
You have to see Me. Please, if you don’t
mind, come this side and this side.
Are there any Sahaja yogis?
She’s a Sahaja yogini. No?
Not yet. All right,
move on, move further.
I’m sorry for this, really.
[Marathi]
Now!
Only for people who are sitting on the chairs,
not who are sitting on
the ground are all right.
Are there some people this
side, can go this side also?
Can you move so that you can come
this side, please, all of you?
Can you move this side?
There is room. Because there’s
some people sitting behind.
if you don’t mind, if
you could come this side.
Some of them can come
here. Please come.
Yes, some of you can move
this side, please. Thank you.
Can you come here please, all of you?
Yes, please.
You, too, madam, come along, this side.
All of you come along.
Now, before we start ...
Won’t you come this side?
There is room here, please.
Hello
They are Sahaja yogis? All right.
The people who are sitting
on the chair should put
both their legs or feet
apart from each other,
because these are two powers
on the left and the right.
The left one is the power of desire,
of the common desire;
kundalini is the pure
desire, power of pure desire.
The right one is the power of action.
This looks after...  left side
looks after our emotions,
the right side looks after our
physical and mental activities.
So you have to put your
left hand on your lap,
very comfortably on your lap, left hand,
towards Me. This is symbolic
that you want to have your Self-realisation.
Now, there are two
conditions we have to fulfil
in Sahaja Yoga.
First one is that you
have to be in the present.
That means you have to forget the past.
To be very frank
you have to know that you
are not guilty of anything.
Please have no guilty feeling within you.
This feeling is absolutely hypothetical
and has no meaning.
Actually, when you feel guilty
this centre on the left-hand side
is sometimes so ruined
that you get horrible diseases like angina,
lethargic organs, and also spondylitis.
So what’s the use of having such
a illogical thing like a guilt?
If you were guilty really,
you would have been in jail.
So please believe in yourself.
Have faith in yourself
that you are not guilty at
all. This is very important
because if this centre is catching,
which I feel very much is catching today here,
kundalini won’t rise above. So please,
please, please just forgive yourself
and know that you are not guilty.
Many people are told,
you are sinners,
you are this and that. I tell
you, don’t believe them.
Because I feel to tell
even this is a sin.
Nobody has right to
tell someone like that.
So please have no guilt
about it. Just forget it.
The animals don’t have
any guilt of anything.
Only we with our own thinking have
created this institution of guilt.
Now the second condition is that
you have to forgive
everyone,
in general.
So see logically again:
whether you forgive
or don’t forgive,
you don’t do anything.
What do you do?
“I cannot forgive. I’ll try to
forgive.” But what is there?
You don’t do anything; it’s
just a mental process.
But if you don’t forgive then
you play into wrong hands,
absolutely.
And this centre of Christ catches,
terribly.
If you don’t forgive,
this centre
which is very constricted
and Christ had to be...
go, had to go through
that and resurrect
Himself to establish
this centre within you.
He has given us the greatest
weapon of forgiveness.
So you have to forgive
everyone in general.
Don’t think who is wrong,
who has done me wrong
nothing of the kind.
Because when we do not forgive
we play into wrong hands.
The person who has
troubled us, tortured us,
is enjoying life.
But when we do not forgive that person,
what happens to us, that we play into
wrong hands and we torture ourselves.
Please remember, that is very
important that you should all forgive.
Throughout Australia My
programmes have been
and every time I meet them they say,
“Mother, I never felt any cool breeze.”
Then I have to go on
working on them:
“forgive, forgive, forgive,
forgive, forgive” and it works.
So why not cooperate with Me a little
bit, just to say, “I forgive everyone.”
Just to say, in general, just forgive.
If you could just say that,
it will really help Me a lot.
You’ll also feel much lighter, much lighter.
You are carrying this load for nothing at
all. So these are the two conditions.
And the third is a promise:
that you should have full
confidence in yourself
and believe that you are going
to get your Self-realisation.
Most of you will get today.
Some if they do not get, may...
we try to get them today,
and then later on they can come.
But also you must promise
that you should not just
allow yourself to be drifted away.
Like Christ has given a parable,
that some seeds were thrown
onto lands which were marsh
of course, the rocks were all wasted.
But on the marshy lands,
and they just sprouted and finished.
So you have to grow into your trees,
to get to your beings, which is so great.
That’s a promise from you,
and that will help a lot.
Because, you see, Divine
also has common sense.
It doesn’t want to work out
people who are good for nothing.
It’s not meant for frivolous people.
You see, if you know that this
light is not going to work out,
why will you try to correct it?
So we have to understand our value.
We have to understand our role,
how important it is.
And it’s such an important
time at this time,
we should not miss it out.
After all, you have been seeking
and seeking gives you the right
to get to the Self-realisation
and then the Divine
has a right to expect
that you’ll spread the light
all throughout the world.
You’ll be surprised, when
I went to Russia first,
twenty-five Germans rushed
” Sahaja yogis ” to Russia.
I was really touched. I
said, “How are you all here?
They said, “Mother, isn’t it our duty?
Whatever done by our
forefathers we have to undo.”
And with such gentleness,
with such sweetness.
you won’t believe these German Sahaja
yogis are one of the gentlest ones.
They handled these Russians,
gave them so much love,
so much attention.
And they have taken the
responsibility of the whole of Russia.
So we have to be
conscious of our being
and then all this knowledge will be
much more manifesting through you.
If you do not give,
it won’t come into you. If you
do not open the other door,
no air will flow from this one.
So you have to give. And when
you give, you grow deep also;
like the tree when it grows outward,
it goes deeper.
They’re all related. So Sahaja
Yoga is a collective happening.
It is not individual; you cannot say,
“I do it in the house” and finished.
No,
you have to come to the collective.
It strengthens you, it strengthens others,
and you understand each and everything.
And everyone is so much in unison
and in love, you’ll really enjoy it.
Like a nail which is cut out
of your finger doesn’t grow.
So now
it is not an individual thing,
but it is absolutely a collective thing
and is an open knowledge to everyone,
absolutely open knowledge to you.
You don’t have to pay for
any one of these things.
So may God give you wisdom
and understanding about yourself.
So!
As you put... and now we’ll
show you first of all,
and then you have to do
it with your closed eyes.
But first you see how you
have to nourish your own centres
and raise your own kundalini.
So put the left hand towards Me,
suggestive or symbolic that you
want to have your realisation.
Then you have to put your
right hand on your heart.
We are working only on the
left-hand side with the right hand.
In the heart resides the spirit.
So we start from there.
Then we take our right hand in the
upper portion of our abdomen.
He’ll show you.
Upper portion of our abdomen,
on the left-hand side.
It’s better to put inside your coat.
He’s, he’s a realised soul,
so it’s all right for him!
This is the centre of your mastery,
by which you become a master.
This centre has been
created by great masters,
and it gets awakened.
Then you take your right hand in
the lower portion of your abdomen
on the left-hand side.
This is the centre of pure knowledge,
pure knowledge that you feel manifesting
on your central nervous system,
on your nerves, by which you know
how to handle this power
and work it out.
This cannot be forced on you.
I respect your freedom.
Then we take our right
hand in the upper portion
of your abdomen on the left-hand
side. Again press it hard.
And then on your heart.
Then in the corner of your
left shoulder and your neck,
like this, from the front.
And turn your head to your right, fully,
fully to your right.
This is the centre, as I told you,
you catch when you feel guilty.
So please turn your head to
your right as far as possible.
Then we take our right hand
onto our forehead across,
and put down our head as far as possible.
This is the centre where you have
to forgive everyone in general.
Now we take our hand on
the back side of our head
and push back our head as far as possible.
This is the centre where, without feeling guilty,
without counting your mistakes,
for your own satisfaction you have
to ask forgiveness from the Divine
not just now; I’ll tell you
later on what is to be done.
Now you have to stretch your palm fully.
Put the centre of your palm on
top of the fontanel bone area,
which was a soft bone in your childhood.
Press it properly.
Now push back your
fingers as far as possible
and put down your head as far as possible.
Now push back your fingers,
that’s very important.
Now press your scalp
nicely and move your scalp
not your hand so much, but
the scalp is to be moved,
slowly clockwise, seven times.
Put down your head, please.
Push back your fingers.
Now, push back your fingers, you see,
next time when you do it.
You want to be seated?
All right, come forward.
You can go this side.
There’s room here this
side, you can go this side.
Come along, it’s all right.
Just take out your shoes, now.
You can take out your spectacles,
because you have to close your eyes
and not to open till I tell you.
If there’s something tight on your waist or
on your neck, please loosen it a little bit.
Sit comfortably straight, not backwards
stretching or forwards bending,
but in a straight manner.
Now close your eyes and put the
left hand towards Me on your lap
and the right hand on your heart.
Please close your eyes.
Here now you have to ask Me a very
fundamental question about you.
In your heart you ask Me three times.
You can call Me “Mother”
or you can call Me “Shri Mataji”,
whatever you want to call Me.
“Mother, am I the spirit?”
Ask this question three times.
Please don’t feel guilty, I’m
getting these catches very much.
Just ask this question.
If you are the spirit,
you are
your own master, because
in the light of the spirit
you know how to guide yourself.
So now please
take your hand, right hand in the
upper portion of your abdomen
on the left-hand side.
Here you have to
ask another fundamental
question to Me, three times,
“Mother, am I my own master?”
Ask this question three times.
I have already told you
that I respect your freedom
and I cannot force pure knowledge on you;
you have to ask for it.
So now please put your right hand
in the lower portion of your abdomen
and press it hard,
on the left-hand side.
Here is the centre which
has got six petals.
So please say six times,
“Mother, please give me pure knowledge.”
You have to ask.
Please say that six times,
“Mother, please give
me pure knowledge.”
As soon as you say that,
the kundalini starts rising.
So we have to clear the upper
centres with our self-confidence.
So now raise your right hand
onto the upper portion of your abdomen
on the left-hand side,
and press it hard.
Here now you have to say with
full confidence, ten times,
“Mother, I am my own master.”
Here you have to say
with full confidence, ten times,
“Mother, I am my own master.”
Say it ten times.
Who are these children crying?
They are Sahaja yogis?
You see, this is the problem
is that the gurus, you see,
these false gurus are torturing them.
Now please take your right hand
onto your
heart.
Here again you have to say
with full confidence,
the greatest truth about yourself,
“Mother, I am the pure spirit.”
The truth is, you are not this body,
you are not this mind,
you are not this ego,
you are not these conditionings,
but you are the pure spirit.
So please say it
twelve times,
“Mother, I am the pure spirit.”
Now,
this all-pervading divine Power
which organises everything,
creates everything,
which thinks, above all it loves us,
is the ocean of knowledge,
is the ocean of
compassion and bliss.
But above all, it is the
ocean of forgiveness.
So we cannot commit any mistake
which cannot be dissolved
by the power of this ocean of forgiveness.
So please now raise your right hand in
the corner of your neck and shoulder,
and here
please say sixteen times
with full confidence,
turning your head to your right fully.
With full confidence you have to say,
“Mother, I am not guilty at all.”
Please say it with full confidence.
This is the worst catch
today we have here.
So please say it with full
confidence in yourself,
“Mother, I am not guilty at all.”
Turn your head to
your right, fully.
I’ve told you, whether you
forgive or don’t forgive,
you do not do
anything whatsoever.
It’s just a myth which
you are carrying.
And this myth has
burdened you so much
that you torture yourself.
So now raise your right hand
on your
forehead across,
and very gently put down
your head on your hand,
resting as far as it is possible.
Here you have to say
again with full confidence
and please say it from your heart,
not how many times.  Please
say it from your heart.
Don’t try; just say it from your heart.
It’s very important.
“Mother, I forgive everyone in general.”
From your heart,
not how many times, from your heart.
It’s the greatest weapon you have got.
Now, please take your right hand
on the back side of your head
and push back your head
as far as possible,
holding your hand tight
on the back side, pressing it
down hard on the back side.
Here you have to say,
without counting your mistakes,
without feeling guilty,
just for your satisfaction
please say, from your heart again,
not how many times,
“Oh, divine Power,
if I have done any mistakes,
knowingly or unknowingly,
please forgive me.”
Say it from your heart again.
Push back your head as far as
possible and hold it tight,
on both the sides.
Now please stretch your palm
fully,
and put the centre of your palm
on top of your fontanel bone area
which was
a soft bone in your childhood.
So is important you
push back your fingers,
fully.
Here again,
I cannot force Self-realisation on you.
You have to ask for it.
So now please put down your
head. Please put down your head.
And now
move your scalp slowly,
seven times clockwise,
saying seven times,
“Mother, please give me Self-realisation,”
“Mother, please give me Self-realisation.”
Now please take down your hands,
and open your eyes very slowly.
Very slowly open your
eyes, very slowly.
Put both the hands
towards Me like this.
You stand up.
Higher.
Now put the
head down, and see with left hand
if there’s a cool or a hot breeze
coming out of your own head.
Now don’t doubt it,
please see it clearly.
you have to certify yourself.
Now see clearly if there’s a cool or
a hot breeze coming out of your head.
You shouldn’t put your
hand on top of your head,
or it should be above your head.
Some people do get it very far away.
So try to move it on both the sides
up and down, and see for yourself
if there’s a cool breeze or a hot breeze
coming out of your head,
fontanel bone area.
Now please put the
left hand towards Me.
Again bend your head,
and with the right hand you see.
Gently you can see. It’s
a very subtle thing,
so be careful.
Some people get it as a great rush also,
some get it in a very big way,
but some get it in a very subtle
way. But don’t get confused.
Now please put your
right hand towards Me.
Now bend your head. Bend your head
and see for yourself
if there’s a cool or a hot
breeze of the Holy Ghost
coming out of your head.
Now raise your hands, both
of them, towards the sky.
Raise your hands
and ask a question,
“Is this the cool breeze
of the Holy Ghost?”
or
“Is this the all-pervading
Power of God’s love?”
which is called as “ruh” also,
or “Is this the Paramachaitanya?”
Ask this question. Push back your head
fully and ask this question three times,
any one of them three times.
Ask any one of these
questions, three times.
This is the first time you’ll be
feeling this all-pervading Power.
Now take down your hands, please.
Put your hands like this.
Now watch Me without
thinking. You can do it.
Should I stand?
Just, you are in thoughtless
awareness, just see;
even if you cannot see Me you
are in thoughtless awareness,
absolutely relaxed.
All those who have felt
cool breeze or hot breeze out
of their fontanel bone area,
or they have felt it on their
fingers or on their hands,
please raise both your hands.
The capital of Australia!
May God bless you all.
So many of you have got it..
It’s all over! See, but don’t doubt it,
don’t doubt it. It’s all
over: you can go home
and close your windows and see,
it’s all there.
But you feel extremely
relaxed and happy.
So now,
I know it’s time, but still I
would like to meet you people,
those who have felt the cool breeze.
Those who have not felt the cool breeze
could go into another room and
these people will try to fix it up for you.
But those who have felt it, I
would like to meet them first,
and those who then get
their realisation there
could come and see Me.
But some people did not do it, so
that’s not our responsibility in any way.
In the meanwhile there will
be some very nice music,
and now you will
enjoy this music better.
I would like to have some of the
Canberra Sahaja Yogis to come
and sit and help us in singing
and also some of... some from Sydney.
Come on Peter, come on.
A few from Canberra if they can come.
Shall I announce?  They will know.
John,
this microphone is not working.
Canberra!
You must clap while you are sitting.  Please!
Louder!.
This song is composed by a
Swiss Sahaja Yogis in Hindi
and put to tune also I think.
Hindhi 25.
I would like the audience to participate more.
There is a lot of participation, but a
little more will encourage us much more.
Thank you.
I'm going to request  [unclear]
to play [unclear] traditional rural style
as is played in the villages of India,
before we sing the next song.